<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://github.com/qmacro/thinking-aloud</id>
    <title>Thinking Aloud</title>
    <updated>2021-03-24T14:58:36.166Z</updated>
    <generator>NPM module feed (https://www.npmjs.com/package/feed)</generator>
    <author>
        <name>DJ Adams</name>
        <email>qmacro@gmail.com</email>
        <uri>https://github.com/qmacro</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://github.com/qmacro/thinking-aloud"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://github.com/qmacro/thinking-aloud"/>
    <subtitle>A journal</subtitle>
    <rights>DJ Adams</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2021-03-24 10:55:54]]></title>
        <id>https://api.github.com/repos/qmacro/thinking-aloud/issues/1</id>
        <link href="https://github.com/qmacro/thinking-aloud/issues/1"/>
        <updated>2021-03-24T11:03:40.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Can't help overthinking what I should have as my first entry in this journal. Reminds me of the feeling of starting a new notebook, and agonising over what should be on the first page - it must be neat and permanently relevant. Of course, that's nonsense.</p>
<p>So I thought I'd just start typing. After all, the idea of this journal is to allow me to record thoughts in as friction-free a way as possible. Part of that is having a low barrier to writing, but also a low filter threshold.</p>
<p>Anyway, as usual, I've spent the last hour yak shaving, setting up a little system where I can just hit <code>j</code> and get directly to typing in my thoughts.</p>
<p>Hitting <code>j</code> starts a new <code>tmux</code> 'JOURNAL' session, or attaches to an existing one, and then uses <code>gh issue create</code> to initiate the process. The title is easy - I wanted to avoid any agonising over what I should title each journal entry, so I'm simply using a timestamp. The <code>gh issue create</code> process then takes me into <code>vim</code> whereupon some <code>vim</code> configuration notices that it's a Markdown buffer that I'm editing, and throws me into <code>Goyo</code> which is a fantastic way to focus on writing.</p>
<p>And that's it. I'm not exactly sure whether things will work when I exit this buffer, I guess the only way to find out is to try it. Here goes.</p>]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>
